Inventory of the Arthur L. West papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Arthur L. West papers
1944-1984
1964-1972
84023
Hoover Institution Archives
8 manuscript boxes, 1 motion picture film reel (3.3 linear feet)
Reports, manuals, orders, correspondence, memoranda, printed matter, and photographs relating to American military operations, especially in Vietnam, and to United States Army development of combat systems and tactics, especially the use of armor.
West, Arthur L.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1984.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1919 January 6 Born, Phoenix, Arizona
1937 March 6 Married Trois Argel Meyer
1940 Received B.S. in economics and business administration, Oklahoma A&M College
1940 August 15 Commissioned as 2nd Lieutenant, U.S. Army
1942 February 1 Promoted to 1st Lieutenant
1942 October 5 Promoted to Captain
1943 May 26 Promoted to Major
1943-1944 Battalion Commander, 10th Armored Infantry Battalion, 4th Armored Division
1944 September 9 Promoted to Lieutenant Colonel
1950-1953 Officer, G-3, Plans Division, Department of the Army
1951 Received M.A., Georgetown University
1953 Officer, G-3, X Corps
1953-1954 Officer, G-3, Training Division, Eighth Army
1955 Graduated, Armed Forces Staff College
1955 March 31 Promoted to Colonel
1955-1957 Department Director, Command and Staff Department of U.S. Army Armor School
1958 Graduated, The National War College
1958-1960 Staff Member, Office of Chief of Staff of Military Operations
1960-1962 Strategic Planner, Joint Chiefs of Staff
1962-1963 Commander, Combat Command A, 3rd Armored Division
1963 July 17 Promoted to Brigadier General
1963-1964 Assistant Division Commander, 3rd Armored Division
1964-1966 Director, Organization, Unit Training, and Readiness Directorate
1966 Promoted to Major General
1966-1967 Chief, U.S. Army Mechanized and Armor Combat Operations Evaluation (MACOV) Team
1985 January 3 Died
Scope and Content of Collection
Reports, manuals, orders, correspondence, memoranda, printed matter, and photographs relating to American military operations, especially in Vietnam, and to United States Army development of combat systems and tactics, especially the use of armor. The original order of the files has been maintained. Original folder titles are denoted with quotation marks.
United States. Army--Officers.; Armored vehicles, Military.; Vietnam War, 1961-1975.; Motion pictures.
- "General West's personal file, 1965, Vol I," (Box-folder 1: 1)
- "General West's personal file, 1965, Vol II," (Box-folder 1: 2-3)
- "Vehicles in the Infantry Division Infantry Doctrine and Concepts,", 1954, 1966 (Box-folder 1: 4)
  Scope and Contents note
  Contains reports and memoranda pertaining to the use of armored vehicles in infantry maneuvers.
- "Congratulatory letters re second star,", 1965 (Box-folder 1: 5)
- "ROAD [Reorganization Army Objectives Division] Evaluation & Mech Inf Guidelines, Future & POL [Petroleum, Oils, and Lubricants] Resupply Problem,", 1962-1965 (Box-folder 1: 6)
  Contains reports and correspondence.
- "Training of the Soldier,", 1963-1964 (Box-folder 1: 7)
  Contains plans and correspondence relating to U.S. Army training.
- Miscellaneous papers related to Marshall lawsuit, 1965-1967 (Box-folder 1: 8)
  Contains correspondence, photographs, receipts, and other material relating to a 1967 civil lawsuit between Maj. Gen. West and Robert C. Marshall Ltd. regarding payment for installation of a faulty air conditioning unit.
- Correspondence, reports, and other material, 1963-1970 (Box-folder 2: 1)
- "Confrontation with Gen LeMay," memoranda, 1960, 1984 (Box-folder 2: 2)
  Contains a study "of particular significance" prepared by then-Col. West for the Joint Chiefs of Staff. The U.S. Air Force's lack of cooperation with the study led to "a direct confrontation by a Col of the organization JCS [Col. West] with Chief of Staff, Air Force (Gen Curtis LeMay)," as well as "ultimate change (within 2 years) in National Security policy from Strategy of Massive Retaliation to a strategy that reorganized the requirement + desirability of having capability to fight conventional war."
- "Personal,", 1967-1981 (Box-folder 2: 3)
  Contains correspondence and other material.
- "The Battle at St. Vith, Belgium,", 1962, 1966 (Box-folder 2: 4)
- "Evaluation of U.S. Army Mechanized and Armor Combat Operations in Vietnam, Volume Four: Methods and Procedures,", 1967 March 28 (Box-folder 2: 5)
- "Mechanized and Armor Combat Operations in Vietnam,", 1967 March 28 (Box-folder 2: 6, Box-folder 7: 1)
- Miscellaneous papers, 1967 (Box-folder 2: 7)
- "Industrial Forecasting," reports, 1969 (Box-folder 2: 8-9)
- Reports and correspondence, 1965-1971 (Box-folder 2: 10)
- "Clarke papers,", 1969-1971 (Box-folder 2: 11)
  Contains writings by U.S. Army Gen. Bruce C. Clarke on leadership.
- 1/4 inch tape sound reels, undated (Box-folder 3: 1)
  - "Bayonet Chorus, Soldier Choir out of 3/36 Inf. CCA, 3d AD," 1 reel, 48 minutes, 1962-1963
  - Untitled reel, undated
- 10th Armored Infantry Battalion diary, 1944-1945, 1984 (Box-folder 3: 2-3)
- Armor magazines, 1963-1972 (Box-folder 3: 4)
- Robert T. Goodrow memoranda and paintings, 1967 (Box-folder 3: 5)
- "Efficiency report file,", 1965-1967 (Box-folder 3: 6)
- "Biographical sketch,", 1964 (Box-folder 3: 7)
- Untitled article written by Maj. Gen. West for Armor magazine, 1976 (Box-folder 3: 8)
- "Official photographs,", 1964-1966 (Box-folder 3: 9)
- "General West’s personal file, 1966, Vol II," correspondence (Box-folder 4: 1)
- "General West's personal file, 1967, Vol I," correspondence (Box-folder 4: 2-3)
- "News clippings 3rd AD,", 1962-1963 (Box-folder 4: 4)
- Photographs of 3rd Armored Division garrison by Col. Dennis V. Crumley, 1983 (Box-folder 4: 5)
  Contains 18 photographs of the U.S. Army 3rd Armored Division's garrison, Ayers Kasserne in Kirch-Göns, Germany, taken by a former subordinate of Maj. Gen. West, Col. Dennis Crumley. Photographs are accompanied by notes by Col. Crumley written on the reverse.
- Manuals and other material, 1959-1962 (Box-folder 4: 6)
- Presentation and field manual, 1957, 1984 (Box-folder 4: 7)
  Contains a presentation transcript from The Armored School entitled "Defense by Armor," a Department of the Army field manual entitled Armor Operations Small Units, and a short explanatory note by Maj. Gen. West. The note explains that the mobile defense section in the presentation, authored by Maj. Gen. West, Lt. Cols Russ Richmond, James Spurrier, and Major Bill Lynch, was a revolutionary concept at the time, and was first officially adopted by the Department of Army in the field manual present.
- "MACOV speech,", after 1966 (Box-folder 4: 8)
- Maps of Vietnam, 1965 (Box-folder 6: 3-4, Box-folder 5: 1)
- "The Political Theories of Rousseau, Bentham, Hegel, and Wilson," term paper, 1949 December (Box-folder 5: 2)
- "Great Britain and the Anglo-French Military Conversations During the Period of the First Moroccan Crisis," term paper, 1949 September (Box-folder 5: 3)
- "The Bosnian Crisis," term paper, 1949 December (Box-folder 5: 4)
- "T. H. Green's Concept of Freedom," term paper, 1950 April (Box-folder 5: 5)
- "A Foreign Policy for the United States," term paper, 1950 March (Box-folder 5: 6)
- "The Political Implications of the Military and Naval Provisions of the Armistice,” term paper, 1950 April (Box-folder 5: 7)
- "Background of the Polish Revolution of 1830," term paper, 1949 September (Box-folder 5: 8)
- "A Foreign Policy for the United States," outline for term paper, 1949 November (Box-folder 5: 9)
- "A Study of Coalitions - France, 1918-1919," dissertation, 1951 February (Box-folder 5: 10)
- "General West's personal file, 1966, Vol I," correspondence (Box-folder 5: 11-12)
- "Climatic Charts of Southeast Asia,", undated (Box-folder 6: 1)
- "Concept of Operations Briefing - CDC [Combat Developments Command],", after 1962 (Box-folder 6: 2)
- "Comparison, New Mech Inf Bn [Mechanized Infantry Battalion] with all other Inf Bns,", 1966 (Box-folder 6: 5)
- "General West's personal file, 1964," (Box-folder 6: 6)
- "General West’s personal file - Civ [Civilian] firms,", 1966-1967 (Box-folder 6: 7)
- Miscellaneous reports, 1971 (Box-folder 6: 8)
- Miscellaneous papers, 1967-1971 (Box-folder 6: 9)
- "Leaders Guide for Operations in Southeast Asia," manual, 1965 August (Box-folder 6: 10)
- "Training Text 17-37-1 Air Cavalry Squadron,", 1967 August (Box-folder 7: 2)
- Correspondence, plans, and memoranda, 1967-1969 (Box-folder 7: 3)
- "MACOV backup," correspondence and other material, 1965-1967 (Box-folder 7: 4)
- "SCI [Systems Consultants, Incorporated] Consulting Agreement,", 1971-1972 (Box-folder 7: 5)
- "Retirement info, citations etc.,", 1967-1970 (Box-folder 7: 6)
- "Trip reports,", 1964-1966 (Box-folder 7: 7)
- "MacArthur’s Address to Congress,", 1951 (Box-folder 7: 8)
- "MACOV Study Plan,", 1966 (Box-folder 7: 9)
- Miscellaneous papers, 1964-1968 (Box-folder 8: 1)
- "Systems Consultants Employment,", 1969-1973 (Box-folder 8: 2)
- Correspondence, 1969-1970 (Box-folder 8: 3)
- "Work Resumés,", undated (Box-folder 8: 4)
- "Combat Footage - Vietnam 1966-1967," 16mm film (Reel shelf)